<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short apologie for Christian souldiours wherein is conteined, how that we ought both to propagate, and also if neede require, to defende by force of armes, the Catholike Church of Christ, against the tyrannie of Antichrist and his adherentes: penned by Stephanus Iunius Brutus, and translated into English by H.P. for the benefite of the resolution of the Church of England, in the defence of the gospel.</title>
            <title>Vindiciae contra tyrannos. Part 4. English</title>
            <author>Languet, Hubert, 1518-1581.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05066</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105564</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841291</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841291</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5865</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05066)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5865)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 573:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short apologie for Christian souldiours wherein is conteined, how that we ought both to propagate, and also if neede require, to defende by force of armes, the Catholike Church of Christ, against the tyrannie of Antichrist and his adherentes: penned by Stephanus Iunius Brutus, and translated into English by H.P. for the benefite of the resolution of the Church of England, in the defence of the gospel.</title>
                  <title>Vindiciae contra tyrannos. Part 4. English</title>
                  <author>Languet, Hubert, 1518-1581.</author>
                  <author>H. P., fl. 1588.</author>
                  <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, for Henry Carre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Stephanus Iunius Brutus = Hubert Languet. Also sometimes attributed to Philippe de Mornay.</note>
                  <note>An English translation of Part 4 of the "Vindiciae contra tyrannos".</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An apologie for Christian souldiours.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Duties --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Despotism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5865:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5865:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT Apologie for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Souldiours: wherein is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, how that we ought both to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate, and alſo if neede require, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende by force of armes, the Catholike Church of Chriſt, againſt the tyrannie of Antichriſt and his adherentes: penned by Stephanus Iunius Brutus, and tranſlated into Engliſh by H. P. for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of the reſolution of the Church of England, in the defence of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <p>O Iſrael if thou returne, returne vnto mee: and if thou put away thine abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s out of my ſight, then ſhalt thou not remoue.
<bibl>Ierem. 4.1.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by Iohn Wolfe, for <hi>Henry Carre.</hi> 1588.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5865:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5865:2"/>
            <head>THE QVESTION. VVhen the Subiects of anie Prince, are either afflicted for Religion, or oppreſſed with tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, it is lawfull for the Princes inhabiting about them, to ſend them ayde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Queſtion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to be vſed than learning, if we will determine any certaine thing thereof: for it is ſuch a one, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which if charitie in theſe our dayes were not become colde, were altogether néedleſſe. But as the maners of men are in theſe dayes, the courſe of the world is come to this point, that there is nothing among vs either of greater price, or of ſmaller prayſe than charitie, and therefore it is a very neceſſarie queſtion to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined of thoſe which are tyrannous Princes, and cruell to their ſubiects, as to their ſoules, to their bodies, to the church of God, to their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, to their owne kingdome, may lawfully be reſiſted for the benefite of the church
<pb facs="tcp:5865:3"/>
of Chriſt, &amp; for the encreaſe of the ſame. But becauſe that either the craftie dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of tyrants is ſuch, or the ſimplicitie of the ſubiects ſo much, that the one is not knowen before he haue ſpoyled his people, and the other perceiueth it not before they be brought to preſent daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and into ſuch narrowe ſtreights, as that they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to craue the aide of other Princes: The queſtion is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, whether it be lawful for other Princes adioyning, to ſend them ayde, they either defending their religion, or their common wealth, or the kingdome of Chriſt, or their owne countrey. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny there are which thinke it lawefull, whoſe couetous minde is ſuch, as they thinke by ayding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to encreaſe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their owne ſubſtance. For ſo did the <hi>Romanes,</hi> ſo did <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, and many other, which vnder the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of expugning the cruell dealings of tyrantes, haue often enlarged their owne liuings. And we haue ſéene but of late dayes, and example hereof in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, king of Fraunce, who vnder a pretence of defending the proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and reducing them from ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude
<pb facs="tcp:5865:3"/>
into libertie, and to preſerue the Princes of the Empire, made warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Charles</hi> the fift. But if at any time it happen, that either the gaine is ſmall or the daunger great, then we ſée many Princes content to make it a great queſtion, and to diſpute doubtfully whether it be lawfull or no. And as the one doth couer his ambition and deſire of gaine vnder the cloke of pietie, ſo the other doth pretende iuſtice and equitie for his excuſe, when as in déede neither pietie doth depart the one, nor iuſtice detaine the other, both of which vertues, or rather diuine qualities, ſéeking alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether thoſe things which may benefite their Chriſtian brethren, and the church of Chriſt. Therefore let vs firſt enquire in the cauſe of religion, what pietie and iuſtice do exhorte vs vnto. It is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that the church of God is one, that Chriſt is the head of the church, whoſe members are ſo knitte and ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the leaſt of them cannot ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer violence, but that the whole muſt alſo gréeue and ſorrowe with it, and therefore the church is compared to a bodie. The bodie doth periſh many
<pb facs="tcp:5865:4"/>
times by a wound receiued, not only in the arme or in the thigh, but euen in the leaſt member thereof. And therefore it is in vaine for a man to ſay that he is carefull for the church of Chriſt, when as he ſuffereth her to be rent aſunder, and be torne in pieces, in whoſe power it is to ſaue her. Furthermore, the church of Chriſt is compared to a buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and a building if it be vndermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in any place, it falleth to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: a building in what ioynte or tenant ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the fire co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, it is wholy in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: and therefore he may well be lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed at, who becauſe he dwelleth in the ſellar, or ſome lower part of the houſe, hath no care to remoue the fire from the toppe of the houſe: or when the enemy vndermineth one part, hath no regarde of it, becauſe he dwelleth on the other ſide. Moreouer, the church of Chriſt is compared to a ſhip, but a ſhip being in daunger vpon the ſea, is wholy in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that if one parte bee broken, the whole periſheth. And therefore they which are in the fore part, are as ſafe as they which are in the hinder parte, and they are as ſafe which are in the toppe,
<pb facs="tcp:5865:4"/>
as they which are vnder the hatches: ſo that it is verified in a common prouerbe among vs, that they which are in the ſelfe ſame daunger, are ſaied to be in the ſame ſhip together. So that he which is not moued with griefe of the bodie, nor with the burning of the houſe, nor with the toſſing of the ſhippe, giueth out a plaine argument, that he is not of the ſame bodie, that he is not of the ſame houſholde, and familie of Chriſt, that he is not in the ſame arke or ſhip, which is the church. But he which is moued, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be neuer ſo little, he muſt as well bring ayde to afflicted members of the church, as to him ſelfe, becauſe in the church of Chriſt we are all one. And it is our bounden dutie, that euery man ſhould aide as much as in him lieth, and ſo much the more, by how much he hath receiued riches at the handes of God, which are not giuen him for his owne poſſeſſion onely, but alſo to be beſtowed vpon his poore brethren, being members with him, according as they haue néede. This church as it is one, ſo is it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended to the patronage of all Chriſtian princes whatſoeuer, for
<pb facs="tcp:5865:5"/>
becauſe it is not ſo ſafe to committe the vniuerſall church to one, &amp; it is againſt the vnitie thereof to commit to euerie one a piece, therefore it pleaſed God to commit the vniuerſall Church to euerie one, and euerie part thereof to the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall defence of al. And this he did, not onely that we ſhould defende it, but alſo that we ſhould encreaſe it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the Germaine Princes do defend the church of Chriſt in Germanie, or the Prince of England in England, &amp; doth not ayde the churches alſo in other countries, but doth ſuffer them to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed &amp; deſolate, they may be thought to haue forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the church: for the ſpouſe of Chriſt is one, which if ſhe be violated and defiled, all Princes muſt ſet to their helping hand to deliuer her. The reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of this vniuerſall church being af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted in part, as it is the dutie of euerie priuate man, with moſt earneſt prayer to deſire at Gods hand, ſo it is the dutie of Magiſtrats by their powers, by their aſſiſtance, by all meanes they can, to raiſe her vp being fallen, &amp; to ſet her in the proſperitie ſhe was before. There is not one church of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:5865:5"/>
another of the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> and of the reſt: but all theſe are parts of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall church, and the vniuerſal church is the kingdome of Chriſt, which kings and princes, and magiſtrates ought to enlarge, propagate, &amp; amplifie, againſt all enemies and aduerſaries of the ſame, and for this cauſe was there one onely temple among the Iewes, built by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> which did repreſent the vnitie of the Church: that builder might be called a fooliſh builder, which making one part of his houſe windtight &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertight, doth ſuffer an other to let in the rayne and the winter. So likewiſe all Chriſtian kings, when they are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the crowne, they receiue the ſworde expreſſely vpon this condition, that they ſhall defende and mainteine the Catholike and vniuerſall Church, the which ſworde when they haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into their handes, they ſhake it to the Eaſt and to the Weſt, and to the North, and to the South, and to all quarters and climates of the worlde. Nowe when they take vpon them the patronage and protection of the church, they vnderſtand no doubt the true, and
<pb facs="tcp:5865:6"/>
not the falſe church, and in her defence they ought to imploy all their induſtrie, force and ſtrength. Of this we haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in godly princes, that it hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes béen obſerued. In the time of <hi>Ezechias</hi> the king of <hi>Iuda,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chro. 31</note> the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Iſrael was in ſeruitude to the king of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> euen from the time of <hi>Oſea</hi> the king. Wherefore if that onely church of God, which was in the kingdome of <hi>Iuda,</hi> and not the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Church was committed to <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias,</hi> and that he had authoritie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Church, no farther than he had to commande tribute, ſurely <hi>Ezechias</hi> eſpecially in thoſe times, in which the <hi>Aſſyria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> were maſters ouer the whole worlde, woulde haue kept him ſelfe within the limittes of the kingdome of <hi>Iuda.</hi> But we reade that he did inuite by meſſengers, the whole people of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, the ſubiects of the king of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> to celebrate the paſſeouer in Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that he did ayde the godly men in Iſrael, in breaking downe the highe places, and ſpoyling the powers of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 22. 2. Chr. 34.</note> &amp; others, which were in ſubiection to the <hi>Aſſyrians.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5865:6"/>
We reade alſo of <hi>Ioſias</hi> the godly king, that he did purge not onely his owne kingdome, but alſo the kingdome of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, ſubiect to the king of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> from the worſhipping of Idols. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> where the cauſe of the glorie of God, and of the kingdome of Chriſt is touched, no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits and bounds ought to abate and quench the zeale of good and godlie prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But if the force of their enemies be great, let them vnderſtand by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of theſe kings, which did truly ſerue the Lorde, that they may not or néede not feare any. Theſe examples of godly Princes many Chriſtian kings haue followed, whereby the Church which was onely within the limits of the lande <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> hath béen, and is ſpredde throughout the whole worlde. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and <hi>Licinius,</hi> were both Emperours, the one of the Eaſt, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Weſt, they were fellowes of like and equall authoritie. It is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, that thoſe which are equall, haue no iuriſdiction the one ouer the other. Neuertheleſſe, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> when he ſawe <hi>Licinius</hi> vnder the pretence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, vexing &amp; killing the Chriſtians,
<pb facs="tcp:5865:7"/>
he proclaimeth warre againſt him,<note place="margin">We muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eade this aduiſedly, becauſe we may not by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he worde of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt our own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rince if he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e wicked.</note> and by force of armes, ſetteth vp the frée ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God to the Chriſtians: and in the ende <hi>Licinius</hi> breaking his league which he had made with him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to his former crueltie, he cauſed him to be put to death at <hi>Theſſalonica.</hi> This did <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, whoſe godlineſſe is ſo much celebrated and ſet out by the Chriſtians in thoſe times, that they ſaid it might very well agree to him, which was propheſied by <hi>Eſaie</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet, that kings ſhould be nurſing fathers, and Queenes nurſing mothers to the church. When he was dead, the Romaine Empire was deuided among his ſonnes, that they ſhould all rule e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually, among which <hi>Conſtans</hi> did fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the Chriſtians, and <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the <hi>Arrians,</hi> which alſo droue out of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria Athanaſius,</hi> an enemy to the <hi>Arrians.</hi> If there were any account to be made of limits and bounds, it were moſt eſpecially betwéene brothers: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe <hi>Conſtans</hi> threatneth his brother, that vnleſſe he reſtore <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> into his place againe, hee woulde come with force of armes againſt him.
<pb facs="tcp:5865:7"/>
If <hi>Conſtans</hi> doubted not to do this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for reſtoring of one Biſhop, may it not more rightly be done, when a great part of the people is oppreſſed, when they humbly require ayde, and deſire that they may kéepe their religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, the nobles of their countrey being chiefe authours in this requeſt.<note place="margin">Sozom. li. 7. ca. 18.</note> So <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> being perſuaded by a Biſhop of <hi>Aſia,</hi> tooke vp armes againſt <hi>Cheſroem</hi> king of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> that thereby he might reſcue the Chriſtians, (being all priuate men) which were vexed in the cauſe of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The which thing thoſe godly Princes which made ſo many lawes, and had ſuch ſpeciall care of Iuſtice and equitie, would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue done, if they had thought or iudged, that they had entred into the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, or gone about to breake the lawes of their Princes in ſo doing. To what end were ſo many expeditions of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes into <hi>Syria,</hi> againſt the <hi>Saracens,</hi> to what ende were ſo many taxes reared, ſummes of money leuied, ſuch warre proclaimed againſt the Turkes, and ſo many forces erected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, if it had not béen lawful for
<pb facs="tcp:5865:8"/>
all Chriſtian Princes, euen for thoſe which dwell fartheſt off, to deliuer the church of God from tyrannie, and from the yoke of ſeruitude. And by what ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and reaſons were they vrged, and ſtirred to take this warre in hande, but onely becauſe the church of Chriſt is one, becauſe Chriſt him ſelfe had cited all able men to take weapon, becauſe that common daungers were to be cut off by common ayde, all which do verie well agrée to this cauſe wée haue in hande. So that if it were lawfull for them againſt <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and not onely lawfull, but alſo that rewards were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to them which did willingly take armes, and puniſhment to thoſe which did detract the ſame, why may we not do the like againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemies of Chriſt? And if we may do it againſt the <hi>Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> beſieging of <hi>Troy,</hi> why may we not do it againſt <hi>Sinon,</hi> which by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting cities and houſes on fyre, doth rob and ſpoyle. To conclude, if it be a godly acte, to deliuer the Chriſtians from bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſeruitude, (for the <hi>Turkes</hi> compell no man) is it not much more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the ſight of God, to deliuer their
<pb facs="tcp:5865:8"/>
ſoules from the ſlauerie of Sathan, to place them in the cleare light of the Goſpel: and theſe ſo many examples of godly Princes, may be vnto vs inſtéede of a lawe. But nowe let vs here what God by the mouth of his Prophets doth denounce againſt thoſe, which either do not promote the inſtauration of his church, or make no account of the great affliction thereof. The <hi>Gadits</hi> and the <hi>Rubenites,</hi> and the halfe tribe of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes,</hi> do demaunde of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 32. Ioſu. 4.7.12. Deut. 3.</note> that hée would giue vnto them and their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their portion, on this ſide of <hi>Iordan:</hi> and Moſes gaue it them, but vpon this condition, that they ſhould not onely helpe their brethren the Iſraelites, in obteining of the lande of <hi>Chanaan,</hi> but alſo becauſe they had firſt receiued their portion, they ſhould go before them, and place them ſelues in the firſt ray: but if they would not, then he would curſe them, and compare them vnto thoſe which were iudged rebels at <hi>Cadeſbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea.</hi> For (ſaith he) ſhall your brethren make warre, and ſhall you lye at peace, nay rather ye ſhall come ouer <hi>Iordane,</hi> neither ſhall you go backe to your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb facs="tcp:5865:9"/>
before the Lord hath driuen out his enemies before his face, and haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen reſt vnto your brethren as vnto you: then ſhall ye be founde innocent before the Lord, and before Iſrael: and thoſe to whome the Lord hath giuen ſuch a benefite, as to haue their portion firſt, thoſe he wil laye great puniſhment vpon, vnleſſe they helpe their brethren, vnleſſe they be partakers of their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and go before them into the land of <hi>Chanaan.</hi> Likewiſe when the men of <hi>Nepthali,</hi> and the men of <hi>Zabulon, (Debora</hi> being their Captain) did take armes againſt <hi>Iaben,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. 5.</note> being a tyraunt, and the tribe of <hi>Ruben</hi> did ſport and delight him ſelfe with his pipe among the heards of cattle, which ſhould haue béene foremoſt, and firſt haue armed him ſelfe: <hi>Galead</hi> thought him ſelfe ſafe, the riuer béeing betwéene him and his enemies: <hi>Dan</hi> boaſted that he was maſter of the ſea: <hi>Aſher</hi> put his truſt in the ruggedneſſe of the rocke: the ſpirit of the Lord ſpeaking by the mouth of the Propheteſſe, condemned them all: curſe ye <hi>Meroz</hi> ſaith the Angel of the Lord, curſe the inhabitantes thereof,
<pb facs="tcp:5865:9"/>
becauſe they came not to help the Lord, againſt the mightie. <hi>Iael</hi> the wife of <hi>Heber</hi> the <hi>Kenite,</hi> ſhall bee bleſſed aboue other women, bleſſed ſhall ſhe be aboue women dwelling in Tents. Notably it is ſaide of <hi>Vrias</hi> vnto <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> the Arcke of Iſrael and <hi>Iuda</hi> dwell in tents, and my Lord <hi>Ioab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.</note> and the ſeruants of my Lord, abide in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen fields, and ſhall I then goe into my houſe to eate and drinke, and companie with my wife? by thy life, and by the life of thy ſoule I will not do this thing. Moſt wicked is that of the people of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, which taking their eaſe in <hi>Sion,</hi> &amp; truſting in the mountaines of <hi>Samaria,</hi> lye vppon beds of Iuorie,<note place="margin">Amos. 6.</note> and ſtretch them ſelues vpon their beddes, and eate the lambes of the flocke, and calues out of the ſtall: they ſing to the ſound of the viole, they drinke wine in bowls, and anoynte them ſelues with the chiefe oyntments, but no man is ſorrie for the affliction of <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> Therfore the Lord God hath ſworne, I abhorre the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of <hi>Iacob</hi> and hate his palaces, I will deliuer vp the citie with all that is therein, therefore nowe ſhall they goe
<pb facs="tcp:5865:10"/>
captiue with the firſt that goe captiue.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ud. 8.12.</note> Moſt wickedly did the <hi>Ephraimites,</hi> which did not only reioyce with <hi>Gedon</hi> and <hi>Iepthe,</hi> hauing gotten the victorie, but alſo did enuie them: and when they were in daungers did forſake them. Wickedly did the Iſraelites. which cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out to <hi>Dauid</hi> when he had the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, behold we are thy bones and thy fleſh, which before when he was driuen into narrow ſtreights, ſaid, we haue no part with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sam. 5.</note> nor in the ſonne of <hi>Iſhaie.</hi> Wickedly do all thoſe which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians only in ſhewe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, are content to bee preſent at the ſpirituall banket, but refuſe to taſte of the cuppe of bitterneſſe together with their brethren, which content to ſéeke for their ſaluation in the church, not withſtanding they haue no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of the ſafetie and welfare, either of the Church or of the members there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And farther alſo they are content to acknowledge one God for their father, one Chriſt for their redéemer, one holy ghoſt for their ſanctifier and preſeruer, one houſe and familie of the faithfull, one miſticall bodie in Ieſus Chriſt: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:5865:10"/>
they do not bring their ayde vnto Chriſt being afflicted in his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, nor ſende their ſuccour to their poore brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their extremities. This vngodlineſſe is great, and what puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is neceſſarie for ſuch as offende in this point?<note place="margin">Num. 32.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> compareth thoſe which forſake their brethren in their daungers, to thoſe rebels of <hi>Cade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea,</hi> whereof not one entred into the lande of <hi>Chanaan,</hi> according to the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of God. And let thoſe men ſéeke for no place in the heauenly <hi>Chanaan,</hi> which are not deſirous to ſuccour Chriſt him ſelfe béeing both miſerably afflicted, and alſo ſlaine againe euerie day almoſt a thouſand times. Chriſt him ſelfe vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly codemned thoſe which did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him when hée was a ſtraunger, which did not cheriſh him when he was colde, and did not clothe him when he was naked, which did not ſuccour him when he was poore, and laſtly, which did not endeuour to ſet him frée when he was a captiue. Therefore thoſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not thinke but that eternall fire is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them, which euery day both ſée &amp; heare theſe things with their eyes
<pb facs="tcp:5865:11"/>
and eares, and are not moued, ſo that we may ſay iuſtly, it wilbe eaſier for any Infidell at the day of iudgement, then for them. For let vs reaſon thus: did the Iewes only crucifie Chriſt, and the Scribes and Phariſies? Did the <hi>Ethniks</hi> only perſecute Chriſt, and the <hi>Turkes,</hi> and certaine Chriſtians, in his members? The Iewes did beléeue and profeſſe that he was a deceiuer: the <hi>Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nickes</hi> that he was an euill perſon, the <hi>Turkes</hi> that he was an infidell: all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he was an heretick. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if we reſpect their minde and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent whereby al offences are to be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, they perſecuting thoſe whome they thought to be wicked, impious, and vngodly, it doth appeare, that in the proper ſenſe they did not ſlay Chriſt the ſonne of God.<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſalm. 82. Ambro. li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de Offic. Gratian. in decretis.</note> But thoſe do truely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute Chriſt, and thoſe do trulie ſlaye him, which willingly ſuffer him to be afflicted in his members, whome they ſurely know and beléeue to be the ſonne of God, the Meſſias and Sauiour of the world. Finally, he that doth not deliuer a man from daunger when it lieth in his power to doe it, he is guiltie of his
<pb facs="tcp:5865:11"/>
death, as much as he which murthered him: <hi>Quia enim noluit ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ferre, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit occidi,</hi> for, becauſe he would not helpe him, he would haue him ſlaine, &amp; in ſuch crimes the will is ſpecially to be reſpected. But the offence of Chriſtian Princes which do not helpe the afflicted in the cauſe of religion, is the greater: by howe much the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber is greater which are ſlaine, and by howe much the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is more heynous to kill a brother than to kill an other, to ſlay a good man than to ſlay a théefe, to ſlay an innocent man, then to ſlay an hereticke, to ſlay by deceit than to ſlay by ignorance.</p>
            <p>But concerning thoſe which ſend not their ayde, to the afflicted by tyrants, or ſet not to their helping hand with thoſe which take vpon them the defence of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth, let vs alſo diſpute what may be determined. The league be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene them is not ſo ſtreight as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor the manner of aiding ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely commaunded: when as the cauſe of the Church is not handled, which is one among all, and which being one is vniuerſally committed to all: but the cauſe of the common wealth is decided,
<pb facs="tcp:5865:12"/>
which is one in one countrey, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in an other, which is to be defended by the men &amp; power of hir owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. But (ſaith Chriſt) the Iewe is not onely neighbour to the Iewe, but to the <hi>Samaritane</hi> alſo, and to euery man: and we ought to loue our neighbours euen as our ſelues. Therefore it is not onely the dutie of a Iewe to deliuer a Iewe his owne countrey man, but alſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer euerie ſtraunger (if he will fulfill his dutie) out of the hande of his enemy. Neither let any man diſpute whether it be lawfull to defende an other, when as he iudgeth it lawfull to defend himſelfe. Nay, rather it is more lawfull: for he is prouoked to the defence of him ſelfe, either by anger or by reuenge, or by ſome other perturbation of his minde, ſo that in defending of him ſelfe, he doth many times go farther than he ought to do: but in aiding of his neighbour, it is onely charitie that moueth him, and in this aide and aſſiſtance, the moſt immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate man that is, can eaſely obſerue a meane. Here in this point wee may learne of the very <hi>Ethnicks</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, what nature and common ſocietie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth
<pb facs="tcp:5865:12"/>
of vs.<note place="margin">Cicero li. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Offic. ca. 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> For (as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the nature of all men is one, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture herſelfe doth preſcribe thus much vnto vs, that one man ſhould helpe an other whatſoeuer he bee, euen for this onely cauſe, becauſe he is a man: if not, then take away from vs all ſocietie, all fellowſhip among men. So that as there be two foundations of iuſtice, the one that we hurte no man, the other that we doe good to all: ſo there is alſo two kindes of iniuſtice, the one is to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer iniurie, the other not to helpe him that is iniuried. For he which dealeth iniuſtly with any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thereunto by anger, or prouoked by ſome other perturbation, he doeth as it were violently laye his cruell handes vpon his brother: and hee alſo which doth not defende him if he can, is in as great a faulte, as if he ſhould forſake his parents, his friends, or his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey. So that which the one doth, he doth it being moued with anger, which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth but a little ſpace, but that which the other doeth, he doeth it of an euill minde, which is a perpetuall tyrant within him: and the ſudden furie of the
<pb facs="tcp:5865:13"/>
one may eaſely be excuſed, but the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate counſell of the other is no waye to be tolerated. But peraduenture thou wilt ſay, I doubt leaſt I ſhould by ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the one, offer iniurie to the other: nay, rather thou goeſt about to couer thy vniuſtice vnder the couering of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, for if thou looke well into thy ſelfe, thou ſhalt finde that it is not iuſtice but ſome other trifling cauſe, which doeth diſwade thée from doing thy dutie. For either thou wilt not purchaſe euill wil, or ſuſteine the labour, or beare the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or els thou art many times ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, either with thine owne buſines and affaires, or by ſloth, by negligence, by ſluggiſhneſſe, that many times thou ſuffereſt him to be forſaken, whom thou ſhouldeſt haue preſerued. And ſo long as thou doeſt pretende thine owne buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, becauſe thou wouldeſt not ſéeme to iniurie an other, thou falleſt into the other kinde of iniuſtice, for thou doeſt breake the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſocietie, becauſe thou doeſt not ſpende any of thy ſtudy, of thy labour, of thy riches, in defence of it. Theſe things haue the very Heathen Philoſophers done, onely by the rule of
<pb facs="tcp:5865:13"/>
policie, which many Chriſtians ſée not, being ruled by the rule of Chriſtianitie. Hereof riſeth the lawe among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diod. Sic lib. 2. ca. 2.</note> that if a mans neighbour ſéeing him cruelly heating his ſeruant, do not ſéeke to appeaſe him, hee is condemned by that lawe. Hereof riſeth the lawe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> that if one man found an other in the hands of théeues, and did not deliuer him when he might, he was condemned to die: if he did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him, and yet brought not the théefe before the Magiſtrate, he was beaten with whippes, and commanded to faſt thrée dayes. If theſe things were ſo in priuate men refuſing their ayde, more lawful it is and requiſite in godly prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to ſende their helpe, not to defende a ſeruant from his cruel maſter, or a child from his angrie father, but a whole kingdome againſt a tyrant, a whole countrey againſt the furie of one pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man, and an oppreſſed people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, which is neuertheleſſe a common enemy, and a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plague. So that if he neglecte to doe it, doeth he not deſerue not onely as the other did, the puniſhment of a théefe, but rather
<pb facs="tcp:5865:14"/>
ſome tormente inuented for ſuch ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants.<note place="margin">Thucy. li. 1.</note> Herupon ſpeaketh <hi>Thucydides,</hi> that they are not onely tyrants which bring me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into ſeruitude, but thoſe much rather are tyrantes, which haue no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde to repreſſe the cruelty of tyrants: and eſpecially thoſe which would bee called the defence of Gréece and of their countrey, but refuſe to ayde their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey when it is oppreſſed, theſe men be tyrants. For as they do violently gette ſuch gouernment, ſo they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to vſe violence in kéeping of it: becauſe as <hi>Tyberius</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>Lupum auribus tenent,</hi> they holde a wolfe by the eares, which they can not holde without violence, neither let goe without daunger. Therefore to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh one faulte by an other, they heape vp many together, and they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to doe other men iniurie, leaſt they ſhould ſéeme to be iniurious to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues. But that prince which ſtandeth idlely by, and beholdeth the wickednes of a tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and the ſlaughter of the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, taking pleaſure in it as it were in a ſchoole of fence, is worſe then the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant him ſelfe, by howe much he which
<pb facs="tcp:5865:14"/>
ſetteth the fencers together is worſe than the one that ſlayeth the other, and by howe much his offence is more hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous which killeth a man for his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, than his which killed him in his owne defence, either for feare or, of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie. But peraduenture you wil ſay, it is a faulte for a man to meddle with the affaires of others: the olde man <hi>Chremes</hi> in the Poet ſhall aunſwere,<note place="margin">Pompon de regim<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> leg. 36.</note> 
               <hi>Homo ſum: humani nihil à me alienu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> puto,</hi> I am a man &amp; therefore I thinke whatſoeuer pertaineth to a man, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to me. If it bee obiected which ſome ſaye for the cloaking of their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe, that God hath apointed li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits and boundes to euerie nation, and that we may not as it were thruſt in our ſicle into their harueſt, neither is my counſell to the contrarie, that vnder pretence of ayde we ſhould inuade the countrey of an other nation, or chalenge their iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs, or conuey their harueſt into our floures: nor as he did, who beeing choſen arbiter in a cauſe,<note place="margin">Cice. 2. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> iudged it vnto him ſelfe: but rather that we ſhould cut ſhort any prince, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uading the kingdome of Chriſt, any ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb facs="tcp:5865:15"/>
afflicting his own people, any king throwing downe the props and ſtayes of his common wealth. And this wée muſt performe in ſuch ſort, hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect not to priuate commoditie, but to publike ſocietie, for ſéeing that iuſtice doeth wholy concerne others and not our ſelues, and iniuſtice our ſelues and not others, wee ſhall then deale iuſtly when we haue a ſpeciall care of the good and proſperitie of others. Finally, if a prince doe violently breake the bonds of pietie and iuſtice, an other prince may iuſtly and lawfully excéede his owne li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittes, not to inuade the others, but to force him to be content with his owne. If a prince vſe tyrannie towards his people, we ought to ayde no leſſe, than if his ſubiectes ſhoulde raiſe ſedition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him: and we muſt bee the more readier to do it, becauſe the wickedneſſe is more daungerous of many then of one. If <hi>Porſenna</hi> reduce proude <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinius</hi> to Rome againe: much more iuſtly may <hi>Conſtantine</hi> be ſent for by the people and Senate of Rome, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell <hi>Maxentius</hi> a tyrant out of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. If the prouerbe ſay, <hi>Homo homini
<pb facs="tcp:5865:15"/>
lupus,</hi> that one is as a wolfe to an other in crueltie, why may not one man (as the ſame prouerbe hath) be <hi>Deus,</hi> a God to another, for ayde and defence. They did in olde time account of <hi>Hercules</hi> as of a God, becauſe he did vanquiſh and pull downe <hi>Procruſtes</hi> and <hi>Buſyris,</hi> and other tyrantes, which were verie plagues of mankinde,<note place="margin">Cicero 2. offic.</note> and monſters of the whole world. So was the Empire of Rome as long as it continued a frée Empire, it was eſtéemed as a common defence of the whole worlde, againſt the miſchiefe of tyrants, becauſe the Senate of Rome was a refuge to kings, to peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and nations in their calamities. So <hi>Conſtantine</hi> being ſent for of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains</hi> againſt <hi>Maxentius</hi> the tyrant, the Captaine of his armie beeing God himſelfe, whoſe expedition and prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the whole Church did commende, when as notwithſtanding <hi>Maxentius</hi> had the ſame authoritie in the Weſt, which <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had in the Eaſt. Likewiſe Charles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great made warre againſt the <hi>Longobardians,</hi> being ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp thereu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to by the princes of <hi>Italie,</hi> when as notwithſtanding the kingdom
<pb facs="tcp:5865:16"/>
of <hi>Longobardia</hi> was already eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and <hi>Charles</hi> could chalenge no right or title which he had in them. Likewiſe alſo when <hi>Charles</hi> the balde (ſo called) king of Fraunce, had tyrannouſly put to death <hi>Lambert</hi> and <hi>Iamaetius,</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of the countie, which lieth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the riuers of <hi>Sequana</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geris,</hi> and that the nobles of Fraunce did flie to <hi>Lewes</hi> king of the Germains, <hi>Charles</hi> his brother, to craue ayde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Charles</hi> and his wicked mother <hi>Iudith: Lodouicke</hi> heard them moſt willingly in an honorable aſſemblie of the princes of Germanie, by whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent it was decreed, that for the reſtoring of thoſe which were baniſhed by <hi>Caluus,</hi> there ſhould be open warre proclaimed againſt him. To conclude, as there haue béene tyrants ſome in all places, ſo there are examples in all hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoriographers of princes which haue both reſiſted the tyrants, and defended the people. The which examples prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in theſe dayes ought to imitate (that they be not cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted tyrants themſelues) againſt thoſe which deale tyrannouſly with their people, with their bodies,
<pb facs="tcp:5865:16"/>
with their ſouls, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, &amp; with the church of Chriſt. To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude all in one worde: pietie commaundeth vs to defende the lawe of God and the Church: iuſtice commaundeth vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine tyrants, and thoſe which ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe the common wealth: charitie commandeth vs to helpe the oppreſſed &amp; ſuch as ſtande in néede: therefore they which doe it not: take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way pietie, extinguiſh iuſtice, and make no account of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
